<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="core-concepts">
  <title>Core Concepts</title>

  <section id="sect2">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Graph based workflow/business process management engines are common. They
      have areas of commonality, but they also vary greatly in concept
      and implementation. For example, there are differences in how
      concurrency and synchronization are modeled and in how modularity
      and re-use are promoted.
    </para>

    <para>
      We begin with the some definitions, move on to features likely to be
      common across most engines, then explain Sarasvati specifics.
    </para>

  </section>
  <section id="sect3">
    <title>Definitions</title>

    <para>
      Graphs come with a set of common terms. To begin with, a graph is
      made up of a set of things, hereafter referred to as
      <emphasis>nodes</emphasis>
      and a set of connections between
      <emphasis>nodes</emphasis>
      , know as
      <emphasis>arcs</emphasis>
      .
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Graph</emphasis>
          - A set of nodes, with a set of arcs connecting the nodes.
          While graphs have a wider applicability, graph here is
          synonymous with process definition.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Also know as: Process Definition, Network, Workflow
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Node</emphasis>
          - An element of a graph. A node corresponds roughly to an
          action as defined [Workflow previously]. Nodes can be thought
          of as pieces of code, waiting to be executed when their turn
          comes.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Also known as: Vertex, Place
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Arc</emphasis>
          - A directed connection between two nodes.
          <emphasis>Directed</emphasis>
          means that arcs have a start node and an end node. In some
          cases, an arc may have a label, or name.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Also know as: Edge, Transition
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Predecessor</emphasis>
          - If two nodes are connected by an arc then the node at the
          beginning of the arc is the
          <emphasis>predecessor</emphasis>
          of the node at the end of the arc. How nodes are connected by
          arcs defines the order of execution. Generally a node may not
          execute until at least one, potentially many or all, of its
          predecessors have executed. Nodes may have many arcs exiting
          and entering them.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      These definitions cover the parts of a process definition.
      However, they don't cover how that process definition is actually
      executed. When a process definition gets executed, the execution
      is called a
      <emphasis>process</emphasis>
      . Somehow, a process must track which nodes are being executed.
      This is generally accomplished by placing markers called
      <emphasis>token</emphasis>
      on the active nodes.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Process</emphasis>
          - An executing process definition. A process definition may
          have have zero, one or many processes executing at any given
          time.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Also known as: Case, Instance, Workflow
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Token</emphasis>
          - The set of active tokens marks the current process state.
          Tokens generally point to a node which is currently executing.
          Tokens sometimes have associated state, which is a way of
          passing data from node to node.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Also know as: Execution
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


  </section>
  <section id="sect4">
    <title>Sarasvati Graph Execution </title>

    <para>
      Let us start with a simple process definition, the classic 'Hello
      World'. When executed, this process will print out 'Hello, World!'
      and then complete.
</para>

    <section id="sect5">
      <title>Legend </title>
      <para>
        First, we introduce a graphical notation for process definitions and
        execution. Not all the symbols will make sense immediately, but
        they will all be explained.
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/legend.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>


    </section>
    <section id="sect6">
      <title>Single Node </title>
      <para>
        The simplest useful process definition would consist of a simple node.
        Here is the graphical representation:
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts1.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        How will this process be executed? First the engine needs to determine
        where to start execution.
</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Start Node</emphasis>
            - A node at which a token will be placed when process
            execution begins.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        There are various ways of handling this. For example, there may be a
        specific type of node designated for start positions. All nodes
        of this type will have tokens placed in them at process start.
        Alternately, nodes may have an attribute which indicates whether
        or not they are a start node, allowing any node to be a start
        node. Sarasvati takes this second approach.
</para>

      <para>
        Assuming that the 'Hello World' node is a start node, execution
        would begin by creating a new
        <emphasis>node token</emphasis>
        at the 'Hello World' node.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Node Token</emphasis>
            - A token situated at a node. Node tokens track the response
            of the node guard (see below). They may also have
            attributes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        With the addition of the node token, the process would now look like:
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts1-1.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        As you can see, the node now has an active node token stationed on it.
      </para>

      <para>
        At this point the node has not yet been executed. Before it can
        be, its
        <emphasis>guard</emphasis>
        would need to be invoked.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Node Guard</emphasis>
            - Nodes have functionality associated with them, which will
            be executed when a node token is accepted into the node.
            However, before a node is executed, its guard will be
            executed. The guard is allowed one of three responses:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Accept</emphasis>
                - The node will be executed.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Discard</emphasis>
                - The node token will be marked as discarded and the
                node will not be executed.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Skip</emphasis>
                - The node will
                <emphasis>not</emphasis>
                be executed, however, processing will continue as if the
                node had completed execution normally.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        By default, a node's guard will return Accept. The node will
        then be
        <emphasis>executed</emphasis>
        . This should cause 'Hello, World!' to be printed out.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Node Execution</emphasis>
            - When a node is executed, whatever custom logic has been
            assigned by the developer will run. To complete node
            execution, the node must inform the engine that that the
            given node token has been completed. Node completion may
            happen synchronously as part of the execution of the node
            function or it may happen later, asynchronously.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        As there are no further steps in the process, it is now
        <emphasis>complete</emphasis>
        and looks like:
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts1-2.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Process Completion</emphasis>
            - A process with no active tokens is considered complete.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>



    </section>
    <section id="sect7">
      <title>Two Nodes</title>
      <para>
        Let's now example a slightly more complicated example. Instead of a
        single node, we'll have two, the first of which prints out
        'Hello', the second prints out 'World'. It looks as follows:
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts2.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        The
        <emphasis>Hello</emphasis>
        node is a
        <emphasis>predecessor</emphasis>
        of the
        <emphasis>World</emphasis>
        node. This dependency is indicated by the directed arc.
      </para>

      <para>
        As the
        <emphasis>Hello</emphasis>
        node is marked as a start node, a node token will be placed
        there when the process begins executing.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts2-1.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        When the node token on
        <emphasis>Hello</emphasis>
        is completed, an
        <emphasis>arc token</emphasis>
        will be generated on the outgoing arc.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts2-2.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Arc Token</emphasis>
            - A token situated on an arc. Arc tokens exist so that join
            nodes (see below) know when to execute. Arc tokens may not
            have attributes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        Since the arc on which the arc token is situated goes into a
        <emphasis>non-join node</emphasis>
        , a node token will be created on
        <emphasis>World</emphasis>
        immediately.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Non-join node</emphasis>
            - A node which is activated whenever an arc token arrives on
            an incoming node. Activated means the incoming arc token is
            completed and an active node token is created. This stands
            in contrast to a
            <emphasis>join node</emphasis>
            , where active arc tokens must exist on all incoming arcs
            with the same name.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        The process now looks like:
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts2-3.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        The
        <emphasis>World</emphasis>
        node will now run its guard and then execute. Finally the node
        token will be completed.
      </para>


      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts2-4.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>




    </section>
    <section id="sect8">
      <title>Split and Join with Wait States</title>

      <para>
        Let us now examine an example which contains concurrent execution.
      </para>

      <para>
        The process describes an approval process.
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A request is made
      </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Two approvals must be obtained
      </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The request is granted
      </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        The process looks like:
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        This a simplified system, since it does not allow approvals to be
        denied.
</para>

      <para>
        There is more than one way that this process could be executed.
</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If the approvals are granted by people, the nodes will
            almost certainly be executed asynchronously. This means that
            when a token arrives at
            <emphasis>Approval 1</emphasis>
            , the node will generate a notification to the user who is
            to do the approval. The token will then enter a
            <emphasis>wait state</emphasis>
            . Execution may continue elsewhere in the process, but this
            token will wait until the user enters the system and grants
            approval.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If approvals are done by software which does a check and
            then returns immediately the tokens will not have enter a
            <emphasis>wait state</emphasis>
            , but may continue immediately.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Wait State</emphasis>
            - When a token enters a node and the node is executed, it
            may choose not to immediately continue process execution at
            the end of the node method. In this case the token will
            remain in the node until it is complete asynchronously.
            While the token is waiting to be completed, it is considered
            to be in a wait state.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        Let us view process execution for both these cases, starting with the
        case where approvals are done by people and thus tokens will
        need to enter wait states.
</para>

      <para>
        Execution will begin as usual, by placing a node token in the nodes marked as
        being start nodes.
</para>

      <para>
        The
        <emphasis>Request</emphasis>
        node will be executed. It generates a task for the requester to
        complete. Until the requester has filled out out the request and
        completed the task, the token will be in a wait state. During
        this time the process will look like:
      </para>


      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-1.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        <emphasis>Question:</emphasis>
        What happens once the
        <emphasis>Request</emphasis>
        has been completed? Which arc or arcs will arc tokens be
        generated on?
      </para>

      <para>
        <emphasis>Answer:</emphasis>
        Sarasvati requires that an arc name be specified when completing
        a node token. All arcs with this name will have arc tokens
        generated on them.
      </para>

      <para>
        Some things to note:
</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Most arcs have no name specified. They are considered to have the
            'default' name.
      </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Usually when completing a node token, the default arc name will be given.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Each arc will have an arc token placed on it in turn. No specific
            order is guaranteed
      </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When an arc token is placed on an arc, it will continue on to its end
            node immediately and see if the node can be executed.
      </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>


      <para>
        So now the node token on
        <emphasis>Request</emphasis>
        has been completed and arc tokens will be generated on the
        outgoing arcs. First a node token will be generated on the upper
        arc (though order of arc execution is not guaranteed).
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-2.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        This arc leads to a node which can be executed. The arc token
        will be completed and a node token will be placed in the
        <emphasis>Approval 1</emphasis>
        node.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-3.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Here the node token will enter a wait state. Since no further execution
        can take place here, an arc token will now be generated on the
        second outgoing arc.
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-4.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Again, since node
        <emphasis>Approval 2</emphasis>
        can be executed immediately, the arc token will be completed and
        a node token will be created. It will also enter into a wait
        state once the notification to the user has been created.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-5.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        At some point one of the approvals will be completed. Let's say
        that it's
        <emphasis>Approval 2</emphasis>
        . This will mark the node token complete and generate an arc
        token on the outgoing arc.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-6.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Now the engine will see if the
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        node can be executed. However, as the dashed border indicates,
        the
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        node is a
        <emphasis>join node</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Join node</emphasis>
            - When an arc token arrives a join node, arc tokens must
            exist on all other arcs
            <emphasis>with the same name</emphasis>
            before the node will accept a node token.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        Since there are two arcs with the 'default' name coming into
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        , and only one of them has an arc token, the node can not be
        executed at this time. Execution will halt at this point.
      </para>

      <para>
        At some point later, the token at
        <emphasis>Approval 1</emphasis>
        is completed. This generates an arc token on the outgoing node.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-7.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Now when the engine tries to execute
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        it finds arc tokens on all the incoming 'default' arcs. These
        arc tokens are marked complete and a node token is generated on
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        .
      </para>


      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-8.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Once the
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        task is finished, its node token will also be completed and the
        process will be complete.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-9.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>



    </section>
    <section id="sect9">
      <title>Multithreading</title>
      <para>
        As seen the previous example, a process may have multiple tokens
        active concurrently. Does this imply that each token executes in
        a separate thread? No. Concurrency here is like that of multiple
        programs running on a single chip. Each runs in turns, but may
        present the appearance of running simultaneously.
</para>

      <para>
        However, true multithreading can be done at the node level. Each node when
        executed, may hand off its work to a background thread. The node
        token will then enter a wait state, and other nodes may be
        executed. When the background task is complete, it may then
        complete the node token, allowing further execution.
</para>

      <para>
        Note that only one thread may safely execute the process at any given
        time, and care must be taken to serialize access to the process
        itself.
</para>


    </section>
    <section id="sect10">
      <title>Split and Join without Wait States</title>
      <para>
        Lets now take a look at the same process, except now the approvals will
        be done by software and will not require a wait state.
</para>

      <para>
        The execution will be the same up to the point where
        <emphasis>Approval 1</emphasis>
        is executing.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-3.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Previously, the node token went into a wait state. This time, the approval is
        done synchronously and the token will be completed. This will
        generate an arc token on the outgoing arc.
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-10.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Again, the
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        node is a join node, so it will wait for an arc token on the
        other incoming arc before executing. Execution will continue on
        the lower outgoing arc of
        <emphasis>Request</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-11.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Execution will continue into
        <emphasis>Approval 2</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-12.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        This execution will also finish synchronously and an arc token will be
        generated on the outgoing arc.
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-13.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Execution will finish as before now that all required incoming arcs have
        tokens on them.
</para>



    </section>
    <section id="sect11">
      <title>Flow Control with Guards using Skip</title>
      <para>
        Now that we've seen how execution can split across arcs and join nodes
        can bring current executions back together, let us examine how
        to select which outgoing arcs receive tokens and which nodes get
        executed.
</para>

      <para>
        This example uses almost the same process as the previous example. The
        difference is that either or both approvals may be optional,
        depending on what is being requested.
</para>

      <para>
        Let us pick up execution after the request has been entered and an arc
        token generated on the upper arc:
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-2.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Now the node token will be generated in
        <emphasis>Approval 1</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-3.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        However, remember that this does
        <emphasis>not</emphasis>
        mean that the node will immediately execute. First the
        <emphasis>guard</emphasis>
        must be invoked. Up until now, the guard has always been assumed
        to just return
        <emphasis>Accept</emphasis>
        . This time however, the guard is intelligent. It will check to
        see if this approval is required. If not, it will return a
        <emphasis>Skip</emphasis>
        response.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Skip</emphasis>
            - A guard response which indicates that the node should not
            be executed, but that execution should continue on the
            outgoing nodes. An arc name may be specifying indicated
            which arcs should be used. If no arc name is given, arcs
            with the default name (unnamed arcs) will be used.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        Assume that
        <emphasis>Approval 1</emphasis>
        is not required. The node token will marked as having skipped
        the node, and execution will continue on the outgoing arc.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts3-16.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>



    </section>
    <section id="sect12">
      <title>Flow Control with Guards using Discard</title>
      <para>
        Having seen Skip, let us examine how to use the Discard response from
        guards. The same basic process definition is used, only this
        time, the assumption is that only one of the guards is required.
      </para>

      <para>
        The graph now looks like:
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts4.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Because we are using discard, only one token will reach
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        . This is why the
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        node is no longer a
        <emphasis>join node</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <para>
        Execution begins as normal. We pick up execution where a node
        token has been generated in
        <emphasis>Approval 1</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts4-3.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        In this case, the guard determines that
        <emphasis>Approval 1</emphasis>
        is not required, and returns a
        <emphasis>Discard</emphasis>
        response.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Discard</emphasis>
            - A guard response indicating that the node token should be
            marked as discard, the node should
            <emphasis>not</emphasis>
            be executed and no tokens will be generated on outgoing
            arcs.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        The process now looks like:
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts4-4.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        The node token has been discarded, and execution has continued
        from the completion of
        <emphasis>Request</emphasis>
        where an arc token has been generated on the lower outgoing arc.
        Execution will now continue.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts4-5.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        <emphasis>Approval 2</emphasis>
        will accept its node token and will continue normally.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts4-6.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts4-7.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Remember, because
        <emphasis>Grant</emphasis>
        is no longer a join node, it will have a node token generated on
        it as soon as any arc tokens arrived.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts4-8.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>



    </section>
    <section id="sect13">
      <title>Flow Control with Guards using Named Arcs</title>
      <para>
        This same basic process could be implemented using a guard which returns
        Skip along with an arc name.
</para>

      <para>
        In this variant, a
        <emphasis>Select</emphasis>
        node has been inserted after
        <emphasis>Request</emphasis>
        . This node has no functionality, it only exists to give the
        guard a place to run.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts5.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Let us pick it up after process started, as
        <emphasis>Select</emphasis>
        has a node token generated on it, and its guard is invoked.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts5-3.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        The
        <emphasis>Select</emphasis>
        guard will return a
        <emphasis>Skip</emphasis>
        response which includes the arc name on which to exit.
        <emphasis>All arcs with this name will have an arc token
          generated on them</emphasis>
        . In this case, let us say the guard determines that
        <emphasis>Approval 2</emphasis>
        is required. It returns
        <emphasis>Skip two</emphasis>
        . An arc token is then generated on all arcs named
        <emphasis>two</emphasis>
        (of which is there only one in this case).
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts5-4.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        From here execution continues as normal.
</para>



    </section>
    <section id="sect14">
      <title>Flow Control from Node Completion using Named Arcs</title>
      <para>
        As mentioned previously, when a node token is completed, an arc name
        must be specified. Arc tokens will be generated on all outgoing
        arcs with that name. So the previous example could also be
        implemented like this:
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts6.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Instead of using the guard on the
        <emphasis>Select</emphasis>
        node, the
        <emphasis>Request</emphasis>
        node will specify which arc to exit on.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts6-1.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        If we again specify
        <emphasis>two</emphasis>
        , then an arc token will be generated on that arc.
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts6-2.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        From there, execution will continue.
</para>



    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect15">
    <title>Graph Composition and Nested Processes</title>
    <para>
      Much like any software, a set of process definitions can grow larger,
      more complex and more intertwined as time goes. One solution used
      in the broader software world is encapsulation. This involves
      pulling out common functionality and breaking up large pieces into
      smaller components. These same techniques can be used with a set
      of process definitions. Rather than using copy/paste, sections of
      process definitions that are common can be extracted. Large
      process definitions can be split out into smaller components.
    </para>

    <para>
      Sarasvati supports two ways of doing encapsulation, each with it's
      own advantages and disadvantages. The first is
      <emphasis>graph composition</emphasis>
      , the second is
      <emphasis>nested processes</emphasis>
      . Both of these techniques allow complete process definitions and
      components that have been split out to be defined in separately.
      The difference lies in when they are composed.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Load-time composition</emphasis>
          - Graph composition brings the disparate elements together at
          load time. The main definition being loaded may refer to other
          definitions. These definitions will be loaded as well and they
          will all be combined into a single definition. This single
          definition will execute as if it had been defined in a single
          file.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Run-time composition</emphasis>
          - Nested processes use composition at runtime. The main
          definition will be loaded. When this definition is executed, a
          node may start a nested process. This nested process will
          execute and when completed, the main process will continue.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Now that we have general idea of how graph composition and nested
      processes compare, let us investigate them in more detail.
</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Graph composition</emphasis>
          - The set of process definitions may be seen as a single,
          disconnected graph. A node may contain arcs to nodes in other
          process definitions. These arcs are referred to as
          <emphasis>external arcs</emphasis>
          . When the process definition is loaded, referenced external
          process definitions will be loaded as well. All the process
          definitions will be composed into a single, larger graph. The
          external arcs will become regular arcs. The same external
          processes definition may be embedded more than once. Each
          <emphasis>external instance</emphasis>
          of an external process definition will be given a unique
          identifier.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Advantages
          </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Interactions with external process definitions are not limited to a single
                  node. The connections may be as complicated as within
                  process definition.
              </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Since the graph is not nested, execution is simple.
              </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  All nodes will share a single process variable scope, allowing
                  easy sharing of variables.
              </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Restrictions
          </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Recursion is not allowed, since this would lead to an
                  infinite loop during loading.
                  <emphasis>NOTE:</emphasis>
                  As in regular programing, recursive structures can be
                  implemented using non-recursive techniques.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  All nodes will share a single process variable scope. Sometimes it
                  is desirable to have shared state for a subset of the
                  nodes in a process definition.
              </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The version of an external graph is set when the process
                  definition is loaded, rather than when nodes from that
                  graph are executed. If an external process definition
                  is updated, process definitions referring to it must
                  be reloaded as well to pick up the changes.
              </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>External Arc</emphasis>
          - An arc which has an endpoint in an external process
          definition. While normal arcs are always specified as
          originating in the node where they are defined (aka
          <emphasis>out arcs</emphasis>
          ), it is not possible to add arcs to an external process.
          Therefore external arcs may either be
          <emphasis>in arcs</emphasis>
          or
          <emphasis>out arcs</emphasis>
          . Note that external arcs may be
          <emphasis>named</emphasis>
          just like regular arcs.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Out Arc</emphasis>
              - An arc which starts in the defining node and ends in a
              specified node
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>In Arc</emphasis>
              - An arc which starts in a specified node and ends in the
              node in which it is defined.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>External Instance</emphasis>
          - A specific external process definition may be referenced
          multiple times. It may also be imported into the referring
          process definition multiple times, or just a single time. Each
          external arc names a specific instance of the external process
          definition.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Nested Process</emphasis>
          - A node in an executing process may create a separate, new
          process (of the same or different process definition). This
          new process is known a nested process. The new process gets
          initialized with the process state of the containing process
          and the current token. When the nested process completes, the
          token in the containing process will be completed.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Advantages
          </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The nested process will have it's own process state
              </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Processes may nested recursively
              </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Nested processes will always use the latest version process
                  definition at the time the node is executed.
              </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Restrictions
          </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The interaction with the nested process must all be contained by a
                  single node. The nested process will execute in
                  isolation. The nodes in the nested process won't
                  interact with the those of the containing process in
                  any way.
              </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>



    <section id="sect16">
      <title>Graph Composition Example One</title>

      <para>
        Let's look at an examples of how this works in practice. Here is
        a small process definition which we want to embed. This process
        definition will be named
        <emphasis>ext</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts-externals1.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        It only has two nodes. Notice that both nodes are join nodes, even
        though one node has no inputs and the other only has one.
        However, in the composed graph these nodes may have more inputs.
      </para>

      <para>
        Next is the process definition which will be using
        <emphasis>ext</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts-externals2.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        This process definition looks very different from previous examples. It
        isn't even fully connected.
</para>

      <para>
        Some things to note:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The external arcs are labeled with the process definition name,
              instance and node name that they are intended to link to.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              In this case, all the arcs are connecting to the same
              instance of
              <emphasis>ext</emphasis>
              , instance 1.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Both in and out external arcs may connect to any node in the target
              external. They are not limited to just start nodes, for
              example.
      </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        When the graph is loaded, the composed version will look as
        follows:
      </para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts-externals3.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>


    </section>
    <section id="sect17">
      <title>Graph Composition Example Two</title>
      <para>
        The previous example referenced only a single instance. Here is the
        example using two instances 'ext.
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts-externals4.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        When it is loaded, the composed graph looks like:
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts-externals5.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        As you can see, we now have two copies of
        <emphasis>ext</emphasis>
        embedded in the process definition. One copy will be made for
        each unique instance referenced. A process definition can have
        references to any number of different external definitions and
        each external process definition can be imported any number of
        times.
      </para>


    </section>
    <section id="sect18">
      <title>Nested Processes Example</title>
      <para>
        The above example could not be implemented with nested processes
        because a nested process must be represented by a single node in
        the parent process. So, here is a similar, but simpler example
        using nested processes.
</para>

      <para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/concepts-nested1.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>
      </para>

      <para>
        Nodes
        <literal>S</literal>
        and
        <literal>T</literal>
        both refer to the nested process named
        <literal>nested</literal>
        . Note that
        <literal>nested</literal>
        is almost the same as
        <literal>ext</literal>
        , except that the first node is a start node. This is because
        <literal>nested</literal>
        will be executed as a separate process. If it didn't have a
        start node, it would not execute.
      </para>

      <para>
        When
        <literal>S</literal>
        and
        <literal>T</literal>
        execute, each will spawn a separate process. When
        <literal>S</literal>
        is executed, it will have an incomplete node token
        <literal>t</literal>
        . As part of execution it will start a new
        <literal>nested</literal>
        process
        <literal>P</literal>
        which have have the token
        <literal>t</literal>
        as a parent. When
        <literal>P</literal>
        completes, it will check if it has a parent token, and finding
        that it does, will complete
        <literal>t</literal>
        . This will allow execution to continue in the original process.
      </para>


    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect19">
    <title>Execution Environment</title>
    <para>
      While executing your process definitions, it may be desirable to
      have some shared state or to send data between nodes via the
      tokens. Sarasvati supports both these things via the execution
      <emphasis>environment</emphasis>
      . Each process has an environment on which attributes/variables
      can be set. In addition, each token also has its own environment.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Environment</emphasis>
          - A set of key/value attributes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      When using a memory backed engine, all environment attributes are
      stored in memory. However, when using a database backed engine, we
      may wish to persist only certain attributes. Also, storing objects
      in the database can be complicated, storing arbitrary objects in
      memory is easier than doing so in the database. By default,
      attributes are
      <emphasis>persistent</emphasis>
      , however, there is a separate set of variables which are
      <emphasis>transient</emphasis>
      .
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Persistent Attributes</emphasis>
          - These attributes will be stored for the lifetime of the
          process. There may be restriction on what can be (easily)
          stored a persistent attribute, since it may need to be stored
          in a database table.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Transient Attributes</emphasis>
          - These attributes will be stored in memory, only as long as
          the process and/or token is in memory. For a memory backed
          engine, these have the same scope as the persistent
          attributes. There are no restrictions on what can be stored as
          a transient attribute.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="sect20">
      <title>Process Attributes</title>
      <para>
        If you want state that is accessible from anywhere during process
        execution, then attributes can be set on the process
        environment. These attributes are visible and mutable by all
        nodes.
</para>

    </section>
    <section id="sect21">
      <title>Token Attributes</title>
      <para>
        Each
        <emphasis>node token</emphasis>
        also has its own environment. Arc tokens do not have an
        environment, because they do not execute in the same way that
        node tokens do, and thus have no need for private state. Node
        tokens are initialized with the state of their
        <emphasis>parent tokens</emphasis>
        .
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Parent token</emphasis>
            - Each node tokens has zero to many parents.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A node token on a start node has no parents. It will start with
                an empty environment.
        </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A node token on a node with one incoming arc of a given name has
                a single parent. Its environment will be copied from the
                parent.
        </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A node token on a join node may have multiple parents, one for
                each arc of the same name. In this case the environments
                of all the parents must be combined in some way. By
                default, each environment will be imported into that of
                the new node. So if more than one parent has an
                attribute with the same one, the last one imported will
                overwrite the previous values. This behavior may be
                overridden, but if this is a concern, then using process
                level attributes may be advisable.
        </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
