<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="what-is-workflow">
  <title>What is workflow</title>

  <para>
    To help understand what workflow is, we start with definitions of
    the main components of a workflow system.
  </para>

  <section id="sect1">
    <title>Definitions </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Actor</emphasis>
          - A person or program which performs some
          <emphasis>action</emphasis>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Action</emphasis>
          - Something to be performed by an
          <emphasis>actor</emphasis>
          . Once an
          <emphasis>actor</emphasis>
          is notified that a given
          <emphasis>action</emphasis>
          is to be completed, they may perform it synchronously or
          asynchronously. It may take hours or days to complete the
          <emphasis>action</emphasis>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Process Definition</emphasis>
          - A set of actions which need to be performed. The actions have a
          defined order in which they must be performed. Some actions may be
          performed concurrently with others.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Process</emphasis>
          - An instantiation of a
          <emphasis>process definition</emphasis>
          . Each
          <emphasis>process definition</emphasis>
          may have many processes running at once. A
          <emphasis>process definition</emphasis>
          can be compared to the on disk image of a program, where the
          <emphasis>process</emphasis>
          is comparable to an executing program (possibly with multiple
          threads of execution). Or from an OO perspective, a
          <emphasis>process definition</emphasis>
          is analogous to a class definition and a
          <emphasis>process</emphasis>
          is like an instantiated object of that class.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Workflow Engine</emphasis>
          - A program, library or API which can load
          <emphasis>process definitions</emphasis>
          and from them, generate and execute a
          <emphasis>processes</emphasis>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Workflow</emphasis>
          - A label for systems which enable the building of
      process definitions and the execution of processes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </section>
  <section id="sect2">
    <title>Why workflow?</title>

    <para>
      So what is so special about workflow? After all, dependencies
      can be handled programatically. If action A is followed by action B,
      then action A can just invoke action B when it is complete.
      Concurrency can be handed by threads.
    </para>

    <para>
      What workflow generally provides over a manual implementation is
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Ease of implementation
  </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If there are complicated dependencies, these are tracked by
              the workflow engine. Each action doesn't need to worry about what
              comes before or after it. This also allows actions to be more
              easily abstracted and reused.
             </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The workflow engine also ideally handles persistence.
              Processes can be long running, taking weeks or months to complete.
              The workflow engine will handle persisting the state of the
              workflow, so if the containing program dies, needs to be update or
              restarted, the process will not be lost.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>

        <para>
          Ease of definition
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Workflow system generally provide an easier way of designing
              and/or specifying process definitions than by doing it manually in
              code.
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Generally workflow systems can read in process definitions in
              a human readable file format.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Many workflow systems also provide visual editors.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </section>
  <section id="sect3">
    <title>Examples </title>

    <section id="sect3.1">
      <title>Example 1: Order Fulfillment</title>

      <para>
        The scenario here is of a small company which sells beach
        balls. They have a process for servicing an order.
    </para>

      <section id="sect4">
        <title>Actors </title>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Sales (person)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Billing (program)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Warehouse (person)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Marketing (program)
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>
      <section id="sect5">
        <title>The process </title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The sales person receives an order and enters it into the system.
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This includes the type number of products ordered and the payment information.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Once this is complete, the order will go to both billing and
              the warehouse.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              While the warehouse people package and ship the order, the
              billing system will perform whatever credit card transactions are
              necessary.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Once the product is both shipped and billed, a marketing
              system will determine what promotional material and/or
              special offers to send to the customer, in order to elicit future
              business.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>
          Graphically, the process could be represented as follows:
        </para>

        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/example1.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="sect3.2">
      <title>Example 2: Document conversion</title>

      <para>
        This scenario concerns a news aggregation company called NewsCO
        which takes in news from various sources and republishes it in a variety of
        formats. Here we will look at a simplified workflow which handles
        two input formats.
        </para>

      <section id="sect6">
        <title>Actors </title>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              RSS -> NewsCO XML format Converter (program)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Plain text -> NewsCO XML format converter (program)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Editor (person)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              NewsCO XML web publisher (program)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              NewsCO XML Analyzer (program)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              NewsCO XML RSS publisher (program)
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>
      <section id="sect7">
        <title>The process </title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The process begins when an article arrives, either from an RSS feed
              or via a file drop in plain text format.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Conversion:
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If the article is in RSS format, the RSS XML will be converted to
                  a proprietary XML format (the NewsCO XML format)
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If the article is in plain text, it will be parsed and converted
                  to the NewsCO XML format.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If there is an error in the conversion process, the article will
                  be handed to a human editor who will manually do the conversion
            </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Publishing
             </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The NewCO XML will be converted to a webpage and posted on a web
                  site for consumption by the public. The web publisher is an
                  asynchronous program which accepts XML and later provides
                  notification when the publishing is complete. This could be a
                  separate workflow.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  NewsCO customers receive RSS feeds of articles based on keywords. The
                  article will be scanned for keywords. A database entry will be
                  created.
               </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Each customer who has expressed interest in a keyword found in the
                  article will have their RSS feed updated with a link to the
                  published web article.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>
          Graphically, the process could be represented as follows:
        </para>
        <informalfigure>
          <graphic fileref="../images/example2.jpg" />
        </informalfigure>

      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
