<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="why-graph-based-workflow">
  <title>Why graph based workflow?</title>

  <section>
    <title>Graphs and Processes</title>

    <para>
      Graphs have been used for a long time to visually represent processes. Some
      examples are:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flowcharts">Flowcharts</ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Unified Modeling Language (UML)
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Activity_diagram">Activity diagrams</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/State_diagram#UML_state_diagram">State Machine Diagram</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite_state_automata">Finite State Automata</ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Graphs are visual, intuitive and ubiquitous. That finite state machines are
      graphs shows their expressive power. A graph combined with some
      storage is roughly equivalent to a Turing Machine, capable of
      executing any computation.
    </para>

    <section id="why-graph-based-alternatives">
      <title>Alternatives </title>
      <para>
        There are other ways of representing workflows. For example, one could
        just list out the actions along with their dependencies. The
        engine could then properly sequence the actions, For example, the
        simple Order Fulfillment example could be defined as
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enter Order for Sales depends on nothing
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Bill Customer for Billing depends on 1
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ship Product for Warehouse depends on 1
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Market to Customer for Marketing depends on 2, 3
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>
        While this would work fine for simple processes, it doesn't offer a way to
        define cycles. If, for example, the warehouse people determine that
        they are out of stock, they may need to send the workflow back to
        the sales department so they can interact with the customer. This
        mechanism also lacks a clear means of flow control. A single workflow
        could potentially cover the order fulfillment process for many
        different product types. It is likely that some sections of the
        workflow would only apply to specific products.
     </para>

    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
